Guide to the Theodore C. Ruch Correspondence
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
Theodore C. Ruch correspondence
1932-1960
Ms Coll 37
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
0.5
(1 box)
Theordore C. Ruch, physiologist and primatologist, received his Ph.D. at Yale in physiology in 1933. The collection contains both sides of the correspondence between Ruch and his mentor, John F. Fulton, as well as related correspondence to/from Ruch or Fulton and others. Subjects include the publishing of Ruch's Bibliographia primatologica in 1941, Ruch's work with Fulton on editions of William Henry Howell's Textbook of Physiology, and the organization of physiology at Washington University, where Ruch became department chairman, and at Yale.
Ruch, Theodore Cedric, 1906-
Fulton, John F. (John Farquhar), 1899-1960
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Correspondence donated by Ruch's daughter, Libby O. Ruch, 2009. Photographs and Ruch's guide for feeding primates were donated by Libby Ruch in 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Theodore C. Ruch received a B.A. in psychology from the University of Oregon in 1927 and a master's degree from Stanford University in 1928. As a Rhodes Scholar he studied physiology at Oxford University where he obtained a B.A. in 1930 and a B.Sc. in 1932. He received his Ph.D. in physiology at Yale in 1933 working with John F. Fulton. He remained in the department as a fellow, an instructor, and, from 1938 to 1946, as an assistant professor. In 1946 he left New Haven to become chairman of the department of physiology and biophysics at the University of Washington School of Medicine. From 1961 to 1971, he served as the first director of the Regional Primate Center at the University of Washington. He remained associated with the Center until his retirement in 1976. Ruch died in Santa Barbara, California in 1983.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains both sides of the correspondence of Theodore C. Ruch with John F. Fulton, as well as letters to and from publishers and others, regarding the publication of Theodore C. Ruch, Bibliographia primatologica: a classified bibliography of primates other than man (1941); Ruch's work on later editions of William Henry Howell 's Textbook of Physiology, edited by Fulton; and general correspondence with Fulton. Ruch discusses his organization of the department of physiology and biophysics at the University of Washington and his work on primates. The two photographs show (empty) animal cages in Fulton's Laboratory of Physiology.
Arrangement
Organized in two series: 1. Correspondence. 2. Additional material on John F. Fulton.
Physiology; Primates as laboratory animals; Publishers and publishing; Photographs; Physiologists; Primatologists; Bibliographia primatologica; Howell's textbook of physiology; Ruch, Theodore Cedric, 1906-; Thomas, Charles C.; George Banta Publishing Company; University of Washington. School of Medicine; Yale University. Department of Physiology
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Primate bibliography, 1935, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Correspondence of Theodore C. Ruch and John F. Fulton on Ruch's plan to publish a bibliography on primates and his attempt to get money from the Guggenheim Foundation.
  - Primate bibliography, 1940 January- June (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence of Ruch and Fulton with the publisher Charles C Thomas, manufacturing publisher George Banta Publishing Company, and others regarding Theodore C. Ruch, Bibliographia primatologica: a classified bibliography of primates other than man, with an introduction by John F. Fulton. (Springfield, Ill.: Charles C Thomas, 1941). Fulton's original letters and carbons of Ruch's letters are included.
  - Primate bibliography, 1940 July- September (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Primate bibliography, 1940 November- December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Primate bibliography, 1941 January-March (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Primate bibliography, 1941 April-December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Primate bibliography, 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bibliography of primate malaria, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Small amount of correspondence concerning Theodore C. Ruch, Malaria in simian primates: a classified bibliography with annotations, prepared at the request of the Board for the coordination of malaria studies, National Research Council. [New Haven, 1944].
  - Organization of Howell's Textbook of Physiology, 15th ed., . ca. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    List of section editors, instructions for section editors, and section outlines.
    William Henry Howell, a physiologist at Johns Hopkins, published the first edition of this text under the title Text-book of physiology, in 1905. Fourteen editions were edited by Howell, who died in 1940. Fulton took on the task of editing the 15th edition which appeared as Howell's Textbook of Physiology (Philadelphia: Saunders, 1946). Ruch wrote the section on sensation consisting of several chapters.
  - Howell's Textbook of Physiology, 15th ed., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Folder contains correspondence, especially between Ruch and Fulton, but also with others, regarding the preparation of the book.
  - Howell's Textbook of Physiology, 15th ed., 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Howell's Textbook of Physiology, 15th ed., 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General correspondence with John Fulton, 1944, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    On Ruch's new position at University of Washington, the Medical Historical Library at Yale, and a little on the 16th edition of Howell titled, A Textbook of Physiology, published in 1949.
  - General correspondence with John Fulton, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General correspondence with John Fulton, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Textbook of Physiology, 17th ed., 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    This appeared as Textbook of physiology, 17th ed., ed. John F. Fulton (Philadelphia: W.B. Saunders, 1955). Ruch continued to serve as a section editor. These items were in a folder labelled "Textbook."
  - General correspondence with John F. Fulton, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    There is overlap in content with the previous folder.
  - General correspondence with John F. Fulton, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    There is no correspondence with Fulton after 1956. For the 18th edition of the textbook, Medical Phyiology and Biophysics, edited by Theodore C. Ruch and John F. Fulton (Philadelphia: Saunders, 1960), Ruch became the lead editor, with Fulton as second editor. This collaboration is not documented in this collection.
  - Praise of Ruch and Fulton, eds, Medical Physiology and Biophyics, ca. 1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    The folder contains fourteen pages of testimonial quotes for the 18th edition. For the 19th edition, Ruch became the sole editor.
  - Ruch's instructions for feeding laboratory primates, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Photocopy. Libby Ruch has retained the original.
- Additional material on John F. Fulton, Series II
  - John F. Fulton's report to the Secretary of Yale University on the Department of Physiology, 1932 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    26 leaves. Fulton describes the organization of the department, the facilities of the Laboratory of Physiology, and his plans for medical education and training of graduate students. He complains about the excessive amount of administrative and committee work. This is a carbon copy presumably given to Ruch, who was a graduate student at the time.
  - Fulton's service on committees and boards, 1946-1947, and "Bibliography of John Farquhar Fulton," ca. 1932, 1932-1947 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of primate cages at Yale, ca. 1933-1946 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Two photographs of primate cages (without animals) in Fulton's laboratory.